Stanford University alright um as I said
the basic tool of the trade is quantum
field theory and that is what we're
going to spend a little bit of time
learning I'm going to teach you a very
elementary version of what a quantum
field is I think tonight
but I do want to get up on the
blackboard some basic mathematical facts
just to review and to remind you this is
too elementary to be a serious part of
this class at this point but I do want
to get it up there
the first mathematical set of facts does
have to do with waves waves are of
course an example of fields field
configurations fields or things which
vary throughout space waves a particular
kind of configurations in which the
fields are moving in a wave-like motion
and waves and particles are closely
connected through the link of quantum
mechanics I am NOT going to teach a
quantum mechanics course this clod of
this quarter so if your quantum
mechanics is fuzzy uncertain haha go
back to the lectures on quantum
mechanics the two sets
there was a class called quantum
entanglement which we'll get up there
hopefully soon and another class just
called quantum mechanics and that is the
basic starting point for what the
particle physics is also special
relativity but let's just review very
very quickly one mathematical fact which
comes up over and over and over and over
again just what the relation between
sines cosines and Exponential's
everybody probably most of the people
here know this but I just want to get it
up on the blackboard
for future reference okay let's remember
what an exponential is an exponential is
an exponential function
it has the form an e e is a certain
number to the Alpha X X alpha is a
number it could be any number real or
complex or pure imaginary and e to the
Alpha X is a function of X an
exponential is a function which grows in
this case with respect to X by an amount
each separate little interval of X it
grows by an amount proportional to
itself for example a population of a
petri dish the increase in the
population is proportional to the
population itself and so the hallmark of
an exponential let's call this f of X is
that the derivative of f of X with
respect to X is proportional in this
case with the proportional a
proportionality factor alpha times f
itself the rate of change is
proportional to F itself and such a
function is called an exponential and
it's denoted e to the Alpha X or
something it can be a number of times e
to the Alpha X okay that's the hallmark
of an exponential now let me remind you
of some facts about sines and cosines
and then put them together very quickly
sines and cosines you know what they are
they're functions which oscillate like
this that's sine of X and cosine of X is
exactly the same function except shifted
over by 90 degrees and it looks like
that and I'm sure you all know this I
won't bother going into detail but the
important thing about sine of let's say
KX let's call it sine of KX sine of K
where K is a number any number real
number in this case perms X could be
positive could be net could be negative
and the other function of interest is
cosine of K at
alright sine of KX and cosine of KX can
be differentiated both of them and I'll
just remind you what the derivative is
now you'll remind me what's the
derivative of sine of KX with respect to
X the sine of KX with respect to X is
equal to K times cosine KX and the
derivative of cosine with respect to X
is minus K sine KX so neither one of
these is an exponential neither one has
the property that when you differentiate
it you get something back proportion
it's proportional to itself they have
the odd property that when you
differentiate 1 you get something
proportional to the other whether we're
in one case with a minus sign cosine KX
thank you cosine KX so you differentiate
this one you get the other one you
differentiate the other one you get
minus the first one alright so out of
these two you can now build a
exponential but it's an exponential of
an imaginary thing so let's just let's
just do it once and be done with it if
you take the combination cosine KX plus
I sine KX I being the square root of -1
and you differentiate it with respect to
X what do you get you get from cosine
you get minus sine KX plus I I I'm sorry
minus K sine KX plus I K
cosine KX did I do it correctly now I
think I did which is just spend a couple
of minutes doing the Algebra I times K T
times the original thing back again
cosine KX plus I sine of KX in other
words to make a long story short cosine
KX plus I sine KX is the function e to
the I KX when you differentiate it with
respect to X you get I K times the same
thing all right so that's that's an
important mathematical fact that comes
up over and over again sines and cosines
of course the functions which describe
wave-like oscillations either
oscillations with respect to space if X
is a space coordinate there's an
oscillation the La Salette toolspace
if X happens to be time it corresponds
to an oscillation with respect to time I
will come now let's uh let's consider in
a little more detail well not so much
detail but just quick review all right
we have a wave the wave is moving past
us it has a certain frequency and it has
a certain wavelength let me just remind
you of the connections because we use
them we can call f the frequency it's
the number of cycles that pass you every
second frequency frequency and it's
measured in cycles per second
C stands for cycles per second a cycle
is one full oscillation of the wave
another definition now this is
definition Omega is another form of the
frequency it's the angular frequency
measured in radians per second and it's
just equal to pi times F so f and Omega
are the same thing except for a factor 2
pi
ah and I may go back and forth between
them try to keep equations as simple as
possible with as few factors of Pi so
sometimes I may use Omega sometimes I
may use F okay lambda is of course the
wavelength and now for a light wave a
light wave moves at the speed of light
because it's moving past you with the
speed of light the wavelength and the
frequency are related and they're
related by the formula the wavelength is
the distance traveled in one full cycle
and if you multiply that by the
frequency that gives you the speed of
light that's the velocity the frequency
is how long well the inverse of the time
that it takes to go one full cycle so
this is a distance divided by the time
that it takes to go one for the full
cycle and for a light ray this is see if
it's a sound wave then you put the speed
of sound there if it's a water wave you
put the ball speed of water waves there
or whatever it happens to be but will be
of course particularly interested in in
light waves now that's one set of
equations the other set of equations
that we discussed last time just quick
briefly view review of last time is the
equations of quantum mechanics which
relate wave-like motions the particles
and we're not going to go in heavy depth
into the explanation of these equations
for that you go back and open up the the
lectures on quantum mechanics but
nevertheless I'll try to be as complete
as possible or at least as
self-contained as possible or the
important thing when going to quantum
mechanics is a new number Planck's
constant it comes in two varieties two
separate notations there's the old
Planck's constant which was plunks
original notation
and then there's the new Planck's
constant which is the same as which is
this which is the same as the old
Planck's constant except for a factor of
2 pi and that 2 pi is put there so to
save 2 PI's in somebody else's equation
but if they always come up and there's
just no escape from 2 PI's they're
always you're always going to have them
but the other definition is H bar and
that's the old planets a new Planck
constant that's the old clock constant
divided by 2 pi I will simply save 2
PI's by sometimes using H and sometimes
using H bar try to keep the number of 2
PI's to a minimum now armed lambda times
let's say okay yeah that was that's not
an equation that's just a definition and
what is H H is a number which is a tiny
tiny tiny number anybody remember what
it is 6 times 10 to the minus something
34 or something in some units and some
units are another oh that was an
interesting question it sure my email it
showed up somebody questioning whether
the origin of the unit meter pointing
out let's see what does the meter the
meter is one forty millionth of the way
of the circumference of the earth and
said no I was wrong it didn't have
anything to do with this it's 140
million 30 do you think that somebody
just came along and said let's define a
unit which is 140 millionth of the
circumference of the earth no of course
not that unit had been in use I don't
know what it was called a meter or not
in England it was called the yard but
why 140 million why not 140 trillionth
or 140 well because you wanted some unit
that was easy to deal with for a human
being good to measure rope with good to
measure cloth with whatever
and I do believe that the origin of a
unit which is about the length of a
human beings arm predated knowledge
about what the circumference of the
earth was anyway which in fact was known
for a long time but there brother
yeah in any case in standard units
Meteor seconds and kilograms h-bar is a
very small number do either write
something like 10 to the minus 34 yeah
one point that's little H bar that's H
bar H is 6 times 10 to the minus 34 or
whatever and C of course is 3 times 10
to the 8th meters per second 3 times 10
to the 8th meters per second right okay
so this is just a definition of some
number of definition between a relation
between two numbers but the fact is that
the energy of a single photon a photon
associated with a wave of a given
wavelength and therefore a given
frequency notice this equation here
tells you the relationship between
frequency and wavelength frequency and
wavelength are inverse or inversely
related the bigger one is the smaller
the other is the energy of a single
quantum single quantum energy now this
is not the energy of an electromagnetic
wave this is the energy of one quantum
of the electromagnetic wave that's equal
either to h-bar Omega where Omega is the
frequency of the wave the angular
frequency of the wave incidentally the
frequency of an electromagnetic optical
an optical wave one that you can see
with your eye is very very rapid
something like about 10 to the 15 cycles
per second they'll have that right about
10 to the 15
cycles per second so typically Omega is
very very large into the 15 but a little
over per second but h-bar is more than
small enough to to make the energy of a
single quantum very very small if you
multiply these two in the units that
we've been using you get the energy in
joules and you find out that the energy
in joules is very small 10 to the minus
19th or something like that so we take a
huge number of optical photons to add up
to any appreciable macroscopic
conventional energy all right so the
energy and this of course is also equal
to the other Planck's constant times the
other frequency so they're the same
thing are just two different notations
all right now let's talk about momentum
let's remind ourselves about momentum
energy incidentally and momentum are
especially interesting because they're
conserved quantities they're conserved
our total amount of energy is conserved
total amount of momentum is conserved
and therefore the good bookkeeping
device is good for writing balanced
equations and useful among other things
besides being deep momentum is a vector
it points in a direction points
typically in the direction of motion of
an object it's defined by being
conserved okay but having said that it's
defined by being conserved by the fact
that it's conserved we count it and so
forth we can ask what is the momentum of
various kinds of objects in nature and
the first thing we can write down is the
momentum of a non relativistic object
non relativistic object just means one
moving slower than the speed of light Oh
a lot slower a lot slower than the speed
of light a lot slower the momentum of
such an object is proportional to its
mass times velocity and its velocity is
also a vector
if I give you any pulse of radiation
electromagnetic radiation and it's all
collimated along given direction not a
dispersed wave which is going out in a
variety of different directions but in
which everything is lined up and
collimated along an axis then this is
nonrelativistic the opposite extreme is
super relativistic in other words moving
with the speed of light now this formula
is not right for moving with the speed
of light you could plug in for V the
speed of light but what do you plug in
for M remember I told you M is always by
definition the rest mass where we used
to call the rest mass and a photon
doesn't have a rest mass okay its rest
mass zero try to bring it to rest has
nothing but this is not the right
formula nevertheless the right formula
has a look which looks a bit like this
if we were to have used inappropriately
e equals mc-squared
now mainly I'm using this for unix in
order to get units right energy is mass
times velocity squared then of course
mass would be an energy divided by the
speed of light squared all right now if
I as I said inappropriately ascribed to
a photon a mass equal to its energy
divided by C squared the energy of the
photon divided by C squared and then
said that the velocity of the photon was
C in fact more or less somewhat
accidentally I would get the right
answer that the magnitude of the
momentum this should be read as the
magnitude of the moment
Yeah right but the magnitude of the
momentum is the energy of the photon or
the energy of the electromagnetic wave
for any electromagnetic wave all moving
in a constant direction the direction of
the momentum is of course the direction
of motion of the wave that that's easy
but the magnitude of the momentum is the
energy of the wave divided by the speed
of light from that we can say supposing
the wave consisted only of a single
photon now we're using it legitimately
yeah you get the right answer what is
the momentum of a single photon and to
get the momentum of a single photon you
just plug the energy from here into the
formula for the momentum so let's do
that
the momentum for a single photon well
let's let's do it over here momentum of
a single photon let's write photon over
here cannot be read everybody read that
the momentum of a photon and I'm
concentrating now on its magnitude
incidentally the double bar here means
the magnitude of it the direction is
along the direction of the beam of light
or along the direction of the photon
let's plug it in the energy let's see
let's use this formula over here H times
frequency energy is H frequency divided
by C all right what's the frequency
divided by C right or well 1 over the
wavelength of 1 over the wavelength
frequency divided by C I've divided by C
is equal to 1 over lambda right did I
get that right yes frequency divided by
C is 1 over lambda so this is just the
equation
that the photon momentum photon momentum
in magnitude is equal to Planck's
constant that makes it small times the
frequency divided by C which is divided
by the wavelength so the smaller the
wavelength the larger the momentum of
the photon that's a pattern and it's in
some sense the most important fact
coming from quantum mechanics about
particle physics that if you want short
wavelength for the purposes of studying
very small objects the price that you
pay is you have to put a lot of momentum
equals each h-bar Omega of God is that
the fundamental or is that derived from
some symmetry it derives from the
quantum mechanics of a harmonic
oscillator so the place to look it up is
on lectures previous lectures about the
harmonic oscillator I will make use of
those lectures but that's where it comes
from from a deeper point of view will
come will come to the the right
statements although not the
demonstration of them young just
attention this is we have ways
photons are under a wave it has an
amplitude and always have amplitudes but
a photon itself we haven't talked about
it talk to you giving it such a net let
me answer the question now I would I I
know it was there and I was waiting to
get to the right point but why don't I
just say it now right an electromagnetic
wave or any other wave has several
features one of which I have not written
down here
it's the amplitude of the wave now the
amplitude of the wave well okay here are
two waves with the same frequency the
same every and every respect the same
except that as a and here's another one
one of them is just some small number
times sine KX for example maybe the
small one is a sine KX the other one is
a great big numerical multiple which
I'll call a times sine KX they're
exactly the same except one is much
stronger than the other it's got a
larger amplitude a is the amplitude of
the wave and now the question is in
photon language what is the meaning of
the amplitude or another question you
could ask is what is the amplitude
associated with one photon now the
question is a little bit ambiguous
because quantum mechanics always has
uncertainties technically it has
uncertainties and you can't measure
everything simultaneously for example
you can't measure both the amplitude and
the phase of the wave the phase of the
wave is where it's located but never
mind that
or there's a sensible order magnitude
question order magnitude what is the
amplitude that's associated are with a
single photon for example okay the
answer is the following the energy of a
wave now this is a completely classical
statement completely classical statement
the energy of a wave is proportional
k times the square of the amplitude for
example if this was the electromagnetic
field let's say the electric field or
the magnetic field associated with an
electromagnetic wave what's the energy
of an electromagnetic field it's
proportional to the square of the
electromagnetic field so typically the
energy of a wave is proportional to the
square of the amplitude if you take that
good now the energy of the wave is also
proportional to the number of photons in
that wave
so here I've described for you some
features of a single photon but a wave
of light consists of many photons let's
suppose the number of photons in some
wave of light is in then the energy is
proportional to n in fact the energy
will be in the number of photons times H
bar Omega so that means that there's a
proportionality between the square of
the amplitude on the one hand and the
number of photons in that wave let's
just call it little in the precise exact
detailed connection I'll work out for
you another time but the square of the
amplitude of the wave is proportional to
the number of photons now there's a
factor of H bar in there because the
square of the amplitude is the energy
and we should have an H bar H bar Omega
and the energy so the square of the
amplitude is proportional to H bar and
in now of course the point is that H bar
is an extremely small number this is the
energy of the wave another form another
way of writing the energy of a wave with
many photons not a single photon but
many photons
right now you say well look this is a
terribly tiny number how can you get any
appreciable amount of energy in an
electromagnetic wave well the answer is
by having a lot of photons
so a typical electromagnetic wave that
carries an appreciable energy has an
enormous number of photons to overwhelm
this factor of H bar but the amplitude
if you like a is proportional to the
square root of the number of photons so
that's the missing that's the missing
wave characteristic that I didn't write
down here and as I said it is
proportional to the confusion about the
oscillation we used in a diagram of the
MV field that are perpendicular and
there the temptation to think of that as
a spatial you know the height of the
sine wave
no no right okay right okay so here's a
wave it's moving down the x-axis what's
plotted vertically here is not the
y-axis or the z-axis what's plotted
vertically the electric field right so
this is not a plot there's only one of
the directions here corresponds to space
the other direction of course
corresponds to the electric or the
magnetic field I think that's what you
are asking me to clarify and properly so
now of course the wave could be oriented
in any direction that way that way that
way and the momentum carried by the wave
is along the axis that the wave is
moving yeah say number of photons in the
way oh you you mean number of photons
within one period let's say you move in
one third of it yeah yeah because a
square this is like the powered energy
that's right so that's why this area to
say within one within one wavelength
that's right well the proportionality I
purposefully wrote proportional to here
if we were talking about two wavelengths
three wavelengths for wavelengths of
course the answer but guess you got the
out you got the right idea
well order-of-magnitude it's given by
this formula with n equals 1 but yes in
some sense it is meaningless
it says meaningless for an
electromagnetic wave electromagnetic
wave has both a magnetic field and an
electric field now the magnetic field in
the electric field are related to each
other by a relation which is similar
mathematically to the relationship
between the position of a particle and
the velocity of a particle and those are
things which cannot be measured
simultaneously they are the uncertainty
principle prevents you from knowing both
of them and in the same way there's an
uncertainty principle between electric
field and magnetic field that prevents
you from knowing both of them so yes
there is it there are limitations on how
well you can know the amplitude but as
an order of magnitude statement this is
correct well we'll try to do better as
we go along we're sort of getting into
the subject of quantum field theory
which is a difficult and abstract
subject ok um I wrote down some
equations here which are true for
photons some of them are true for any
particle others are not
alright the definition of frequency
that's the general definition Omega
being 2 pi F that's perfectly good
lambda equals a wavelength that's a
definition this is true for waves which
will move with the speed of light so it
would not be true for a general wave
let's let's put something around those
equations which are not expected to be
of great general generality by great
generality I mean they would be true for
almost any kind of wave or particle
whether or not it moves of the speed of
light this is not so general this is not
so general anything that has a seen it
will not be very general when I say not
general it'll be general for anything
which moves with the speed of light ok
this is general
now energy equals H bar Omega that is
also a very general fact this clearly
neither of these this is specific to
things which move with the speed of
light this is specific to objects which
move with much less than the speed of
light there's an interpolation
in-between which I won't get into now
which is true for things which move with
some fraction of the speed of light so I
can um where were we yeah we were we
were trying to figure out which
equations are great generality which are
not this one
H F over C that contains C in it
that is not terribly general oops
where's my blue momentum equals H
divided by lambda is general okay now
where this comes from I'm not going to
try to prove these things to you now I'm
just telling you as facts go back to
your quantum mechanics momentum is H
over lambda that's general okay let's
use these facts now here's the
relationship for a photon between what
is it arm between frequency and
wavelength and as I said it's not very
general what about a slowly moving
electron or a slowly moving nucleus or
for that matter a slowly moving bowling
ball what's the relationship between
frequency and wavelength can we figure
it out is it something on the blackboard
or something
that we have to add something else
question for an electron I did tell you
last time that electrons are also
described by waves
did I not I told you that you can do
interference experiments with electrons
so there is an electron wave let's call
it Sai
and the question now is what is the
relationship between frequency and
wavelength can we figure it out
yes we can but we need to know one fact
about nonrelativistic systems it's the
analog of knowing it is not the analog
it's knowing the relation between
momentum and energy okay but for an
electron moving slowly the momentum is
not the energy divided by the speed of
light what is it
okay energy is equal to now we can start
at the beginning and right I mean
kinetic energy one-half MV squared and
the momentum MV P equals MV so we can
solve for the velocity P over m
everything is a vector but that's
alright we don't know that's right and
then the energy becomes one-half M times
V squared and V squared is P squared
over m squared if you don't know this
equation it's an important equation it
occurs over and over the energy in terms
of the momentum is one-half P squared
divided by M people get confused the M
is upstairs when you multiply by the
velocity squared its downstairs when you
multiply by the momentum squared okay
now we have what we need to find the
relationship between frequency and
wavelength energy is where is it is
h-bar Omega or H times frequency let's
use H times frequency of a single of a
single electron now we're talking about
a single electron H times the frequency
of the wave describing that electron H
times frequency that's energy on the
right hand side we have one-half
let's put the N downstairs and what
about the momentum the momentum is H
divided by lambda so that's H squared
over lambda squared and we can divide
this equation by H and we find that the
frequency is 1 over 2m times plunks
constant divided by the square this time
of the of the wavelength notice how
different it is are over here the
frequency was proportional to 1 over the
wavelength here it's 1 over the
wavelength squared you don't have to
remember this you have to memorize this
you can always read the rive it the
basic ingredients are the equation for
the energy and the relationship between
momentum wavelength frequency and all
that kind of stuff
all right this is just the illustrate
the connections so that's a non
relativistic particle when moving slowly
for example electron in an atom
the frequency of its Schrodinger wave
would be 1 over 2m times Planck's
constant divided by the wavelength
squared
let me stop me slow down now and pick
some questions that is true for any
particle as long as it's moving slowly
compared to the speed of light
maybe we should well we'll come back and
we'll interpolate between the slow and
the fast another time there is an
interpolation the gino is well depends
on how fast a neutrino is moving most
neutrinos in nature are moving very fast
with close to the speed of light very
close to the speed of light so for
neutrinos the speed of light is a good
approximation for but in principle
neutrinos can be slowed down and if
they're moving with very much less than
the speed of light it's the other
formula a non relativistic formula yeah
and so that's where electrons passing
wait yeah
welcome back to a relation between
amplitudes and and and quanta soon
enough and that's that's what the whole
story is about but we haven't gotten in
an electron accelerator let's say with
20 kV however accelerator with 20 kV
very low energy exhaustion example it's
a slow fest it's a lot to consider slow
or fast damage for an electron slow so
all right well you I could alright um if
you want to know first of all let's work
in units in which C is equal to 1 in
such units momentum and energy have the
same year exactly the same units where
do we have it
momentum and energy have exactly the
same units of C is equal to 1 if you
want to know if something is
relativistic a non relativistic you want
to compare its momentum to its mass if
its momentum is large compared to its
mass its rest mass photon has no rest
mass and so its momentum is always much
larger than its a that its mass and so
it's highly relativistic its
relativistic as it can be the figure of
Merit the thing that you compare is the
momentum to the rest mass so now you
have to tell me what's the rest mass of
an electron you gave me in ke V ok ke V
killer electron volts is a unit of
energy all right and remember energy and
momentum have the same units so what's
the mass of an electron half a million
electron volts so 20 ke V is a lot less
than 20 then half a million and so
that's a slow that's a slow electron
right any other cookies any other
question
frequency and wavelength for a real way
or related yeah start participar
clockwise ready so is that equation the
left one you have did you rewrite a
facebook scheme and get the right
equation but electrons electron waves do
not move with the speed of light so
there's no C so the question is can you
derive a velocity from this yes the
answer is yes you can but it won't be
lost
ah maybe probability well oh there are
two yeah yeah there are two velocities
to go to the waves one of them is called
the group velocity one of them is called
a phase velocity I'll I'll be specific
since you asked me if you take a general
wave the wave let's assume it's a wave
packet now a wave packet means that it
looks like a wave except that it it's
some confined to some packet like
structure like that so it locally looks
like a wave meaning to say a plane wave
a sine or a cosine but it has an
envelope that that sort of combined
confines it to some region now in
general in general depending on the
specific nature of the wave you'll see
that as that wave moves there are two
separate velocities associated with it
and they're different
one of them is the overall velocity of
the wave packet the other is the
velocity of the crests and troughs or
whatever you call them and what you
would see if you looked at this wave
let's say from some other perspective
where you see waves and troughs moving
along is you would see the packet moving
with one velocity but the waves moving
through the packet with a different
velocity in fact typically the wave the
the one is called the phase velocity
that's the velocity of the troughs and
peaks and valleys and the other was
called group velocity the group velocity
is the velocity of the whole packet
guess which one you identify with the
nonrelativistic velocity of the particle
the group velocity and the group
velocity is usually slower than the
phase velocity the phase velocity is not
got to do with the actual velocity of
the particle now there is one special
case the special case is when all waves
of all frequencies move with the same
velocity that would not be true for a
none relativistic wave like this let's
see the velocity is the frequency times
the wavelength right so let's let's look
at this the frequency times the
wavelength is just frequency times
wavelength as 1 over 2m h-bar over
lambda so different lambdas move with
different velocities different lambdas
move with different velocities and when
different wavelengths move with
different velocities you have this
situation where group and phase
velocities are not the same for the
special case where all wavelengths move
with the same velocity then group and
phase velocities are the same so for a
light wave all waves move with the same
velocity the group and the packet
velocity the the group and the phase
velocity are the same that's a special
and simplify a simple case all right but
we didn't I just wanted to illustrate
some of the equations here and
incidentally this equation over here
is equivalent to another equation of
physics anybody know what it is the
Schrodinger equation the Schrodinger
equation is an equation for a wave and
this tells you the time dependence of
the wave the frequency this tells you
the space dependence of the wave the
Schrodinger equation is exactly an
equation for the relationship between
the time dependence of a wave and the
space dependence of the way we will come
back to it but this is just the
Schrodinger equation in a slightly
disguised form for better yet if you
knew the Schrodinger equation and you
said supposing I had a wave of a given
frequency that had a given wave length
what would the equation tell me about
the relation between wavelength and
frequency and it would be exactly this
okay so that's the Schrodinger equation
in a nutshell I think the face velocity
grow faster than life yes yes yes yes
but the phase velocity as a rule carries
no information with it you can't send
information faster than the group
velocity phase velocity doesn't really
carry any any information with it so
we'll come back to that it's it's a
technical issue that we don't need to
deal with right at this moment okay
let's see let's go on a little bit more
with waves there are one or two other
concepts about waves that are necessary
and you know there's a lot of technical
details and I'm getting into but every
single piece of it is really very
central or important okay we will be
interested in waves moving in infinite
space but I use the word infinite space
infinite infinity computers don't like
infinity
and if physics is the art of writing
equations that computers can solve in
principle it is necessary to always
remove the infinities and write the
equations for finite systems first and
then take a limit
all right so in studying quantum
mechanics waves quantum field theory
particle physics and so forth it's
necessary in the back of your mind to
get rid first around of everything
that's infinite and state the problems
as if everything were finite and in
particular what I have in mind now is
the extent of space itself so one way of
what I want you to think about now is a
wave moving in one dimension three
dimensions is really no different than
one dimension except there are three of
them so let's concentrate on one
dimensional wave motion could be a
violin string it could be a rope being
wiggled back and forth or it could just
be a wave in a mathematical universe of
one dimension one way of getting rid of
the infinity of space would be to make
the wave only propagate on a region of
length L for example by holding down the
wave at this end holding down your
string at this in just like a violin
string is held down holding it down at
this end you can have all sorts of waves
and the waves move and they bounce off
when they get to the end they bounce off
and reflect and they go back and forth
and back and forth that's a perfectly
good way to describe things the problem
with this kind of let's call it boundary
condition this is called the boundary
condition namely that waves when they
get to the end reflect it's called a
reflecting boundary condition the
problem with it is it violates one of
the important conservation laws of
physics what would that conservation law
be
momentum after all if the momentum of a
wave is it's a vector quantity it points
in a direction if a wave is moving along
this at has a little wave it's moving
along this axis its momentum is pointing
to the right
when against to the end it bounces off
and reflects so the momentum has changed
sign
okay the momentum has changed sign the
momentum is not conserved that's okay
there's nothing wrong with it you can
study it but if you want to keep track
of things like momentum conservation
there's a smarter thing you can do it
goes as follows imagine this line is
such that we identify the beginning and
the end now we can do that by replacing
the line by a circle it doesn't have to
be a legitimate geometric circle just
mathematically we connect the beginning
back to the a so we go on a cycle
alright so as we move from here to here
to here we can imagine we start here
move along here and in this magic line
when you get to the other end you come
back to the beginning that's a closed
circle I don't want to call it a circle
because I don't mean to imply it's a
circle in two dimensions I just want to
imply that it's periodic periodic is the
term for this periodic space now you can
imagine a wave which is moving along
moving along here and when it comes to
the end over here what does it do it
just keeps going right it just keeps
going it doesn't care about that point
that point is not a special point
anymore and so the wave just keeps
cycling around cycling around cycling
around and the momentum is conserved
it doesn't suddenly reflect into the
direction in terms of this picture you
can just imagine when the wave gets to
this end it reappears at this end and it
just keeps going to the right if it were
going to the right it go
to the left of it we're going to the
left and just keeps going forever with
this trick with this mathematical trick
of replacing space by a periodic space
we can first of all get rid of the
Infinity in the size of space feed it
into a computer and we can get rid of
the problem of momentum of noma of non
momentum conservation momentum is now
conserved but there is a cost I don't
know that it's a cost but it's a fact
the fact is that in such a world
momentum is quantized now I don't mean
in the sense that well it is that
momentum only comes in discrete
multiples of a unit and it's useful to
work in understanding quantum fields
that relation to particles and so forth
is useful to remember that the momentum
comes in discrete multiples of something
so let's see how that works well first
of all it's obvious that the wavelength
an integer number of waves must fill it
let's let's give this distance around
here a name let's call it L L for length
if it were a circle it would be the
circumference but let's just call it L
the total distance around from beginning
back to beginning again quote L all
right if we're going to put a wave in
there and let's say now that it's a way
of a sine or a cosine wave assault
whatever an integer number of
wavelengths has to fit onto the circle
that means that the wavelength has to be
equal to the length around divided by an
integer okay
divided by an integer so the wavelength
must be a total distance around divided
by some integer I don't want to call the
integer in let's see a calculate capital
n
Capital n little n will be reserved for
something else so the wavelength is
necessarily the total distance around
divided by n now that means the
wavelength comes in discrete
possibilities it can be L it can be L
over 2 it can be L over 3 it can be L
over 4 but it can't be L times the
square root of 2 or L divided by the
square root of 2 an integer number of
waves just won't fit in here in other
words if you try to put a wavelength of
the wrong wavelength in here by the time
you got back the wave wouldn't match was
what it was supposed to be at the
beginning ok so that tells you that
wavelengths come in discrete calm
possibilities with the integer appearing
the denominator now we had an equation
here somewheres for momentum in terms of
wavelength what was it
momentum was equal h-bar yes H over
lambda
P is equal to H over lambda so now this
is also telling us that momenta come in
discrete possibilities the momentum of
any quantum must satisfy the constraint
that it's H divided by an allowable
wavelength so the allowable momenta of
quanta the allowable momenta of
electrons the allowable momenta of
photons the allowable momentum of
anything in this one-dimensional world
has to be H divided by okay let's work
it out that's H divided by lambda that
means n divided by L I turned lambda
upside down and over L and what does it
say it says the momenta come in discrete
multiples of a basic unit and the basic
unit is Planck's constant divided by the
total distance around there's a neat
fact if you put a particle and you put
it in if you put a particle on a wire
and the wire is a circular wire a bead a
bead on a wire that bead can only have
momenta which are discrete multiples of
1 over L naught n over Ln is the
multiple 1 over L 1 over the length of
the wire now of course H is a very small
number and the L if L is a big
macroscopic length of wire or something
1 over L is a very small number and so
the quanta the separation between
different mo values different allowed
values of the momenta is very small you
can get own if L is large and H is small
you can get almost any number not almost
any number but you can get a very dense
collection of possible numbers
all right but okay that's the that's the
quantization of momentum in a world in
which everything is periodic yeah total
momentum not total momentum of the of a
of the object total momentum of any
quantum now if every quantum has to have
a integer multiple of this basic unit of
momentum then any number of quanta also
have to have an integer multiple of it
all right you might have each quantum is
identified in terms of its value of in
in terms of its momentum but there are
allowed momentum and disallowed momentum
the allowed momentum are discrete
multiples of a basic unit and any number
of photons electrons and so forth
necessarily come in this discrete
multiples
this is
we get to get stationary model when you
come back to the same place what is that
scene something
well that's the assumption that that the
space is really genuinely periodic that
there's nothing special about any point
and it is a fair question it is a good
question
but it's also the assumption that for
example the electromagnetic wave
electric field is a observable quantity
and it doesn't have sudden jumps in it
in fact a sudden jump you would have if
it didn't come back to itself we would
have to make a sudden jump at this point
a sudden jump is very costly in energy
and in momentum so sudden jumps and
fields fields are continuous things
they're not allowed to jump like that if
you have what what can we package eyes
oh that's alright any packet ah that's a
good word any packetized wave that's a
packetized wave is a sum of individual
plane waves sines and cosines that's the
Fourier analysis the statement the real
statement is any allowable wave is a sum
of waves each of which has this discreet
this discretized the possible values of
momentum so it's a statement about
Fourier transforms that the Fourier
analysis of any allowable wave only has
these discrete multiples of a basic unit
of P
the center problem would help very very
small yeah small as momentum it's very
very very big ah how small very small
you don't wanna get smaller than the
plonk line that's it that's it that's it
that's a bad thing to do up till that
now there's no problem oh we could yeah
what let's pursue this a moment
something that's not in my notes but
let's pursue it it's important let's
really imagine now that we genuinely
have a particle moving on a genuine
circular wire a fun let's really now
take a bead moving on a really circular
wire and see if we can understand what
this quantization of momentum means in
another language let's take the circular
wire to have a radius R let it have a
radius R oh I erased the important
equation what was the important equation
the important equation was the allowable
momentum is equal to an integer times H
over lambda over sorry over L or L right
okay now the radius of the orbit is R
and that means that P is n H over 2 pi
all right you can see by now that h-bar
would have been a better choice in this
equation right let's leave it let's
leave it and later on we'll put back
h-bar okay that's the momentum and the
momentum is quantized every single
electron photon or anything else has to
have an integer multiple of this now
what about the angular momentum what's
the relation
between momentum radius and angular
momentum for a circular orbit for the
simplest possible ah yes it is every R
well for a non relativistic particle its
MV R and we are L stands for angular
momentum MV R but what is MV P so as P
times R now NV r is not completely
general for a relativistic particle the
momentum is not n times V but angular
momentum is equal to momentum times
distance is very general that is for
particle that is the definition of the
momentum at least for a circular orbit
for other orbits it's the cross product
R cross P but it's always R times P and
so now look at this what this says is
that R times P multiplied by our angular
momentum is an integer multiple of H
divided by 2 pi or an integer multiple
of plunks other constant alright so
momentum is another quantity which is
axial angular momentum is a quantity
which is quantized but always in the
same unit unlike the momentum here the
momentum is quantized in a unit which
depends on the angular on loops that I
use alpha 2 things excuse me what should
I call our angular momentum
angular momentum am I will eventually
change that I don't like that but but
for the moment angular momentum alright
is n times H bar momentum is quantized
in this periodic world but the unit of
momentum depends on the length around
the circuit okay
the angular momentum is quantized but
always in units of h-bar okay all
angular momenta come in units of h-bar
except when they don't
when they don't is when you have
fermions but we'll come to that that's
later not tonight
okay there are exceptions to this rule
okay um now we want in the next hour to
invent the idea of a quantum field and
what is a quantum field in the simplest
possible case the simplest possible
situation what exactly is a quantum
field how is the quantum field related
to particles and to its quanta what is
the connection between particles and
fields with some precision and that's
what we'll do next but let's take a
let's take a five-minute break alright
now we have to enter into the real world
of quantum mechanics a little bit and
for that if you're not
our knowledgeable about it you have
various alternatives one is to go to
sleep another is to listen and try to
get you know sort of a what's the right
word for a very impressionistic what
yeah you know get the oh there must be
some word for very impressionistic sort
of soft fuzzy feel for things third is
to go back left what I hope to do better
than that please and the third is to go
back and learn a little bit about of
quantum mechanics there will be nothing
here that I haven't discussed in
previous lectures on quantum mechanics
in particular the most important thing
for our purposes now is one of the
simplest of all quantum systems the
harmonic oscillator why does the
harmonic oscillator come up the harmonic
oscillator is important for a great many
reasons but in our particular context
it's because waves are oscillations if
you just see a wave going past you
obviously the amp with the field
electric magnetic whatever it is
oscillates in fact the fact that
oscillates is equivalent to the
statement that it has a frequency a wave
maybe way made up out of a superposition
of many different wavelengths for
example light you can mix together
different colors of light and create
light of mixed different wavelengths but
you can also separate it as did Newton
into its component wavelengths and so
every light wave can be thought of as
being made up of individual components
each with its own frequency its own
amplitude and so forth
therefore it
be thought up as being made up out of a
collection of quanta and the quanta are
not all of the same energy and momentum
but still it can be separated into
quanta of different energy and momentum
and each energy and momentum is
associated with a wavelength each
wavelength is associated with a
frequency and a frequency is by
definition and oscillation so one can
think of a wave as a collection of
harmonic oscillators harmonic
oscillators being the simplest kind of
oscillation sines and cosines in order
to proceed with what a quantum field is
we have to go back to what the harmonic
oscillator is so let's let's begin with
the harmonic oscillator quantum
mechanics is a strange theory it has
things numbers in it which don't satisfy
the usual rules of arithmetic
technically they are operators
representing the observable things that
you can measure and they have some rules
you can add them you can multiply them
but they don't necessarily commute what
does that mean that means if you have
two variables describing two different
attributes or properties of a system
each of which by itself might be
measurable might be something you can
measure let's call them a and B just to
give them names a could stand for
example for electric field B could stand
for magnetic field or a could stand for
the position of an electron B could
stand for the electric field but any two
pair of things then ordinarily in
ordinary mathematics of course the
product of them doesn't matter which
order you multiply them a times B is
equal to B times a that's just the
property of numbers in quantum mechanics
of course that is not generally true it
may or may not be true of two
observable quantities well it's not true
we just write that the difference
between these is not equal to zero now
what nonsense I mean if I measure the
electric field and it's some number and
I measure the magnetic field and it's
some other number and I multiply them
what how can it possibly be that it
doesn't make sense to multiply them in
the opposite order and get the same
answer generally speaking when the
answer depends on the order of
multiplication what it really means in
other words when this is not zero what
it really means is that you can't
measure both of these things
simultaneously that they interfere with
each other the experiment that measures
one of them necessarily screws up the
measurement of the other one and in that
sense there's no contradiction when this
is not zero simply means you can't
measure both of them together when you
can measure two things simultaneously
and you measure them you get numbers for
them when you multiply the numbers the
numbers have to commute it doesn't
matter which order you multiply them in
and so the test for whether you can
measure two things at the same time is
whether this quantity which is also
called the commutator a B minus B a is
called the commutator of a and B commute
commutator you know like going back and
forth go in to working back you
interchange the order of them it's
labeled by a bracket with a comma and a
and B the order matters so typically
this is not equal to zero
incidentally the commutator of B with a
e that's just exactly the same thing
except in the opposite order and that's
just a sign difference these two are the
same except for a sign okay that the
that's quantum mechanics in a nutshell
we just did quantum mechanics
examples now I'm not proving this I'm
just telling you this now but
nevertheless it's fact partly empirical
fact partly mathematical fact a particle
has different components of position x
y&z for example you can measure the
position of a particle so the components
of position of a particle are candidates
for things which are observables these
things commute with each other you can
measure the X and the y of a particle at
the same time you can measure the X the
Y and the Z of a particle all three
simultaneously what else can you measure
about a particle you can measure its
velocity or its momentum mass times
velocity and those things are called the
components of them are called px py and
PZ they're the components of the vector
momentum and they also commute with each
other you can measure the three
components or better yet the magnitude
and nima and the direction of of the
momentum but you can measure all three
components simultaneously there's no
obstruction they commute with each other
so X commutes with Y commutes with Z P X
commutes with py commutes with PZ but
the components of position do not
commute with the polar components of
momentum so for example you cannot
measure the position the X component of
the position of a particle and the X
component of the momentum every time you
try to measure the X component of
position you will give the particle a
whack and change its momentum and the
result is you can't measure both of them
this is not equal to zero it's equal to
I times Planck's constant it's small
simply reflecting the fact that
well the uncertainties in position and
momentum are small and of order H bar
likewise for the Y components the Y
position and the y momentum don't
commute with each other
same for the Z components how about X
with the y component of momentum can you
measure X and the y components of
momentum simultaneously yes as a matter
of fact you can that that may not be
obvious but it is true okay so that's
another aspect of quantum mechanics and
now let's consider the harmonic
oscillator now I'm telling you facts for
the most part but I'll try to put the
mathematical facts into some kind of
context these are the facts that we went
through previous quarters so I'm not
going to derive it when you go from X to
Y no this is the square root of -1 this
is not the I J this is not our J and K
which are unit vectors along the three
axes and they're also not quaternions
which also have an i J and a K
associated with XY and Z but nope just I
just the square root of -1 where does
the square root of -1 get into a formula
like this don't don't ask we we we don't
we're not going to need it the fact is
we won't really need it we just need to
know that algebraic manipulations in
quantum mechanics are a little bit funny
and the funniness is that you can't as a
rule interchange the orders of our
operations
sir yeah that's not a ap - beer that
means first measure a it doesn't mean
measure this is a it doesn't mean
measure forget measuring are these are
simply mathematical manipulations which
are yeah it doesn't mean first measure a
and then measure B it's simply a not
simply it is a mathematical manipulation
that the matrix multiplication operate a
multiplication yes but we're not going
to we're not going through the
principles of quantum mechanics here I'm
just restating things that we've learned
in the past and if you need to
understand them better the only way to
do it is to go back to earlier lectures
okay
nice and sliced but close there is a it
doesn't really apply to a photon it
applies strictly speaking to
nonrelativistic particles the problem is
that the position of a photon is not so
well defined the position of a photon is
harder to define in the position of a
non relativistic particle so but let's
say we can come back to that
that's a subtlety which is not terribly
important to us now okay the harmonic
oscillator the harmonic oscillator is a
system a classical system which has a
quantum mechanical analog and it simply
means a system which oscillates a weight
on the end of a spring which oscillates
up and down on a sound wave that
oscillates a light wave that oscillates
anything that oscillates like a spring
going back and forth we can think of
thousands of examples and the
mathematics of them is always the same
every oscillation or every oscillator
has a frequency it can either be taken
and we can call it an Omega the
frequency again is 2pi times the number
of cycles per second alright cycle per
second for a spring with a weight on it
is just how long it takes to go through
one full swing and come back to the same
place not just the same place but the
same velocity so if you have a weight on
the end of a spring and it oscillates
it's the the frequency is not how long
it takes to come back to the same place
but how long it takes to come back to
the same place moving in the same
direction so one full oscillation is the
period the number of cycles or number of
oscillations per second is the free
qín C F and as usual Omega is 2 pi F
nothing unusual
the usual Omega now what is unusual
about the quantum mechanical harmonic
oscillator is that energy is quantized
not momentum not the but energy is
quantized this is something which you'll
either look up or accept so let's plot
vertically the energy levels of such a
harmonic oscillator classically of
course there was a lowest energy which
is zero just the oscillator at rest and
then you give it a little poke and it
starts to swing back and forth and you
can give it any positive value of energy
of course if you hit it too hard and try
to give it too much energy you might
melt the spring or I'll break the spring
but in a mathematically idealized
version of the harmonic oscillator you
can give it any positive value of energy
not so the quantum mechanical oscillator
the quantum mechanical oscillator has
discrete integer units of energy if we
call the lowest energy 0 sometimes it's
appropriate to call the lowest energy
not quite zero but we can define we can
define the lowest energy to be zero then
what's the next energy level h-bar Omega
the same formula as the energy of a
photon of frequency Omega what's the
next one - h-bar Omega that could either
be the energy of a single photon
associated with a frequency twice as big
as the first one
or it could correspond to two
Tan's both associated with a wave of
frequency Omega it's the second idea
that I want to dwell on that this has
the same energy as two photons now so
far there are no photons there's only
Springs and balls and oscillations back
and forth but nevertheless this does
have the energy of one photon associated
with a frequency Omega this has the
energy of two photons of frequency Omega
and so forth
three h-bar Omega and so forth those are
the possible energies of the harmonic
oscillator
nothing in between we can label them
with an integer and we can write that
the energy is an integer times H bar
Omega wherein is just an integer which
labels which one of these states the
oscillator is oscillating in it's just a
matter of notation for us here it's just
a matter of notation mathematics of it
we don't need to get into we label the
various states of the oscillator by an
integer N and it's conventional to just
label the states of the oscillator by a
little pointy thing like that
that's called a cat it's called a ket
because it's the right hand side of a
bracket but we don't need the brat in
that we only need the ket end of it and
it's a as I said go back and study
quantum mechanics but all this is all
this labels this is a symbol
representing if you put N equals 0 here
it represents the state of the
oscillator where it's in its ground
state ground state means the lowest
energy state if you put a 1 here it
represents the oscillator oscillating
with one quantum of energy one unit of
energy you put a 2 here it represents
the oscillator with 2 units of energy
and so forth right so it's just a note
it's just a convenient notation for
labeling the various possible
configurations of the quantum harmonic
oscillator
now let's invent an operation it's
actually not only an operation it's an
operate or there's a difference an
operator and this operator acts on a
state to change the state to a new state
so a mathematical operation which takes
you from any state to the neighboring
one one unit above it acts on this state
to give you this one acts on this state
to give you this one so we can write
down what it does let's call it a plus
and the plus indicates that it raises
the energy of a state and then act on
the end state to give one n plus one but
with a coefficient in front of it square
root of n plus one now this is mumbly
jumbly unless you know the bit about the
mathematics of linear operators and so
forth so as I said either you know it
then you can follow it or you don't know
it then you can just get a hazy
impression of what it means but this is
the mathematical property of this
operation here it multiplies any state
vector by a square root of n plus 1 and
raises you to the next level but
basically it's a shift a thing which
shifts you from one level to the next
it's just an operation which shifts you
from one level to the next and we got to
keep track of a numerical coefficient in
front of it what about a - what does it
do takes you down
and minus one what's the coefficient
square root of n square root of n what
happens if this one acts on the bottom
state where does it take you it doesn't
take you anywhere it just gives you zero
that's because if it acts on the bottom
state n is zero and it just gives you
zero nothing no state they're just the
non state there's nothing to get to so
it just gives you zero all right this is
the mathematics of creation and
annihilation operators or raising and
lowering operators now we're just going
to we're going to do some little mumbo
jumbo with it I'm going to show you some
properties of these operations they're
interesting they're entertaining and you
can do some you can have say fun with
them just knowing some very simple set
of rules for it and this is the rules
let's see what happens if we take the
state N and multiply it first by a minus
and then by a plus in other words let's
hit it with a minus and then a plus what
do we get okay all we do is follow the
rules alright so first of all oh one one
important thing some things are just
numbers not everything is one of these
peculiar things that where the order of
multiplication matters some things are
really just numbers things like in are
just numbers that means that the order
that you multiply them doesn't matter
some things the order of multiplication
is perfectly ordinary in in
is always something rather ordinary okay
so what happens what happens what is
this equal to well let's take it in
pieces
let's first multiply a minus by n what
does it give a plus and then a minus
times n is what square root of n times n
minus 1 so let's take that on the
outside and n minus 1 now what happens
if we hit it with a plus if we hit any
vector or any sorry any state with a
plus it raises us back it raises us to
the next level up but multiplies by
square root of n plus 1 but what is
square root of n plus 1 here mean it
just means square root of n since I'm
now starting at n minus 1 hitting it
with a plus will give me square root of
n another square root of n + n square
root of n times square root of n is in
it just gives me the number n times n
that's just a little game that we're
playing we're playing a little game with
a set of logical rules here and what we
find out is if we multiply by a plus and
a minus with this set of logical rules
it's equivalent to multiplying by the
numerical number in whatever state we
put here if we put here the first a zero
state therefore if we put here the
lowest state we get zero if we put here
the first state we get one we put it in
the second state we get two and so forth
so whenever we do this combined set of
operations it picks out for us it picks
out for us the numerical level and tells
us which level we're at if we want to
find out which level we're talking about
I may not know what it is I may just
call it by some other name of Lupus we
just put Lucas here we want to find out
what in blue this corresponds to well we
multiply it by 8 plus time
- and we find out what the numerical
coefficient is that numerical
coefficient tells us what what level of
the oscillator we were playing with so
we can write this in another way we can
simply write that multiplication by a
plus times a minus is the same as
multiplication by n but what is in n is
simply the energy level well not quite
the energy level we need something else
we need H bar Omega we need to multiply
by H bar Omega so we can write in H bar
Omega is H bar Omega times a plus a -
and what does that tell us that tells us
that the energy of the oscillator if we
didn't know what the energy of the
oscillator was we could find out
mathematically mathematical experiment
but as a matter of playing this logical
game we could determine what level we
were talking about by taking the state
unknown state and multiplying it by a
plus a - times H bar Omega now this is a
little game as I said and doesn't
correspond to any actual experiment but
in fact this is the actual energy of the
oscillator okay so that's a mathematical
bunch of tricks bunch of trickery let's
multiply them in the opposite order all
right so what did we find out we found
out that a plus times a minus is equal
to n meaning to say that if you do this
operation on any state it just
multiplies by n what about the opposite
order let's try it in the opposite order
using the same little logical rules a
minus times a plus on n what does that
give did I do that right a minus times a
plus the opposite order so what is a
plus give
this gives square root of n plus 1 times
n plus 1 right and now let's multiply
that by a - a - we'll bring you back
down to n but it will give you another
factor of square root of n plus 1 all
right whenever a - axe it gives you the
numerical coefficient which is the same
as the thing inside here so that gives
you square of square root of n plus 1
times square root of n plus 1 again
times n brings you back down but gives
you the factor overall factor of n plus
1 so what do we find
we found that multiplying in the
opposite order gives us different
answers almost the same answer but not
quite in one order a + a - is N and the
other order a minus times a plus is n
plus 1 so with this little bit of
logical gamesmanship here or
mathematical symbology we find that the
order of these two operations isn't the
singer well what does that mean does
that mean that a plus and a minus that
if we were to measure them and count and
then take the values that we measure for
them the numerical values whatever they
are whatever they correspond to we
measure them that when we multiply their
values by each other they don't they
don't commute that doesn't make sense
numbers always commute when we multiply
them what this means is that whatever a
plus and a minus correspond to you can't
measure both of them simultaneously now
what they correspond to is a combination
of the amplitude of this harmonic
oscillator how big the oscillation is
and it's phase it's phase does everybody
know what the phase of an oscillation is
it's basically the
in which the oscillator passes through
the origin the oscillator can oscillate
back and forth or you can delay it a
little bit so that it goes through the
origin of the later or earlier time you
can't you can't whatever a is you can't
measure it a plus and a minus
simultaneously that's what this tells
you that's all it tells you that they
don't commute and therefore they're not
simultaneously measurable but they're
still interesting mathematical little
objects what do they do what do they do
they are mathematical operations which
raise you up and down this tower what do
they do they add and subtract quanta of
energy of the oscillator
now if the oscillator happens to
correspond to an electromagnetic
oscillation an oscillation of the
electromagnetic field then what these
operators do is they add and subtract
photons they add and subtract photons
they are what are called creation and
annihilation operators all right so
let's up on any physical experiment to
talk about well you can measure the
number of photons but you can't measure
the a plus in the a minus separately you
know it's an interesting question of
whether you can measure a plus or a
minus individually and the answer for
technical reasons is no but but but this
doesn't tell you that okay all right so
we have the idea now of operations or
mathematical quantum mechanical
operations which would make no sense
classically at all we wouldn't we
wouldn't multiply States by the
operators like this but quantum
mechanically we have the idea of
creation and annihilation operators
mathematical operations which add and
act quanta of energy for a fixed
frequency now when we have a system
which has many oscillators you can
imagine we have many Springs with many
balls hanging off from of different
frequencies or you can imagine
electromagnetic waves in a cavity each
different wavelength has a different
frequency we can excite them
independently we can excite one way if
we can excite another wave excite them
independently then we have a system
which contains many different
oscillations with many different
frequencies that means to describe this
may be a good place to slow down a
little bit this is this of course is a
little bit indigestible unless you've
seen it before how many people have seen
it before when no no of course you give
a lecture in another course yeah all
right like a mini lectures on it
probably by now in this I'm not in this
course I have not talked about this yet
oh the sequence of course yes we've
talked about many times I think but the
it certainly is in the lectures on wine
Mari might have been recorded because we
added loot to get me wrong it wasn't
recorded it may not have been to the
work in a different room not represent
set it up about who the next room over
yeah it's okay I hung on a casa later is
the most basic quantum mechanical system
please learn it if you want to follow
these lectures and it is you know you
can you can see where it's going we
describe particles as oscillations and
we create and annihilate particles put
them into the system take them out of
the system by mathematical operations
that are these creation and annihilation
operators so they are absolutely central
to the to the understanding of quantum
field theory and particle physics just
completely ok let's let's come back very
quickly now and I think we'll have to
discuss this again but let's come back
to this little model of a world on a
circle where we made the world finite by
making space to be a circle instead of
an infinite line and now it's a very
simple world of only one dimension but
we have this line distance around it is
L let's imagine photons or
electromagnetic radiation or whatever
kind of particles moving on this line
there are some allowable values of the
wavelength remember where the allowable
values of the wavelength are L divided
by n where n is any integer that means
there are allowable values of momentum
is there are allowable values of
frequency and allowable values of
momentum okay those allowable values of
frequency we can call Omega in
n goes from minus infinity to infinity
whatever it goes over well angles in the
puzzle sorry from zero to infinity all
the possible values of frequencies all
right the waves moving on the system
here are a collection of harmonic
oscillators one harmonic oscillator for
each value of n the each frequency of
oscillation you can add energy
independently to each frequency and you
can take any given frequency and add
energy to oscillations in that frequency
you can then add energy on top of that
with some other frequency so a system of
waves moving on a circle like this so
moving in anything for that matter is
really just a collection of harmonic
oscillators with a certain set of
allowable frequencies the question is
how do you describe this system
mathematically in quantum mechanics and
the answer is let's begin with the idea
of a state we're not going to do this in
detail now we're not actually going to
get to our first example of a quantum
field we'll get there next time but
let's work around it a little bit how
would we label the states of a system
where there are many possible where
there are many oscillators around you
can either think about this as all the
oscillations of a wave on a circle or
you can just think of it as a bunch of
balls and Springs with different
frequencies
how would you label it well each
harmonic oscillator has a quantized
energy the quantized energy for each one
of these oscillators is some integer
times Omega n times H bar so what we
have to state then is the integer
excitations of each oscillator
the number of quanta with the lowest
frequency the lowest frequency whatever
it is or in one number of quanta with
frequency in two or the second the
number of quanta with the third
frequency and so forth and on and on for
infinity forever this would correspond
to a state in which the lowest
wavelength or the longest wavelength the
longest wavelength oscillator
has in one quanta in it the next longest
wavelength oscillation would have in two
and three I'm getting a little bit tired
and I suspect you are also but what I
want you to think about is the guitar
string or the violin string and how you
how you create harmonics what we're
talking about is harmonics all right so
there's an overall mode of oscillation
of the string where it behaves up and
down like that if we forgot everything
else and just thought of this as a
simple harmonic oscillator oscillating
back and forth we could say that the
energy level of the system is just one
possibly no excitations one unit of
excitation two units of excitation three
units of excitation and how much would
each unit of excitation cost it would
cost an energy which was the frequency
of that particular note Omega times H
bar times the number of oscillations
with that frequency then we could add
additional energy in the form of the
first harmonic
all right so if if this oscillation
correspond with the middle C this
oscillation would be what the C one
knocked of above middle C or whatever
add some energy in that that has twice
the frequency twice the frequency so we
would be then adding a number of quanta
with the second frequency and then we
could add oscillations on top of that I
always have trouble drawing this next
one I can't draw it you know what I mean
three with two nodes yeah two nodes but
it would have three times the frequency
right three ways fit in that has an
oscillation like that has three times of
frequency and how many oscillators how
many quanta would we put in or we can
put any number in but that would be in
three and the entire configuration of
this oscillating string quantum
mechanically oscillating string would be
characterized by a collection of
integers which tells us how much
quantized energy there is in each mode
of oscillation so basically what we have
to do mathematically is repeat the
mathematics of the harmonic oscillator
infinitely many times one for each mode
of oscillation
the result is a quantum field that's
what a quantum field is is it's a
collection of harmonic oscillators a
collection of creation and annihilation
operators which add and subtract energy
in each mode of oscillation and it's the
mathematics of that collection of
oscillators which is called quantum
field theory so if we want to carry on
with this subject they have to get used
to this language okay
let's quit here
Wow let me just say one more thing if
we're interested in particle physics
experiments what happens in particle
physics experiments particles with given
energy momentum come in they rearrange
particles with other energy and momentum
go out so in other words we remove
particles with an eye we remove
particles from the initial state and
replace them by particles in the final
state the mathematical description of
that is to remove particles with
annihilation operators and replace them
with particles of other momenta and
energy involving other creation and
annihilation operators so that's what
these operators do they remove particles
and put particles in and the
mathematical description of the creation
and annihilation of particles is through
these kind of mathematical symbols
that's why that's so important the other
the N is used like indicate the energy
level but then it's also used indicate
the count of number of content is that
linkage is going on here one integer has
to do with the number of nodes here and
the other has to do with the number of
quanta I'll spell this out again there
are two distinct integers in this class
in this example the number of nodes
would tell you the frequency and then
the number of quanta with each frequency
so there are two three two integers
floating around
Yeah right one of them is associated
with you yeah this is hard stuff this is
not easy it's abstract it's too abstract
for more please visit us at stanford.edu